Guide to the Council of School Supervisors and Administrators Records WAG.269
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Council of School Supervisors and Administrators Records
1945-2014
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
American Federation of School Administrators. Local 1, Council of Supervisors and Administrators (New York, N.Y.)
Logan, Ernest
Zuckerman, Jacob (Jack)
WAG.269
26.5 Linear Feet (27 boxes)
3 websites in 3 archived websites.
The Council of School Supervisors and Administrators (formerly the Council of Supervisors and Administrators) represents principals and other categories of supervisory/administrative personnel in the New York City school system. It had its origins in a number of separate and relatively powerless associations representing supervisors, and took its present form, as a union chartered by the AFL-CIO, in the aftermath of the crises associated with decentralization and community control of schools and the teachers' strike of 1967-1968. The collection includes minutes, correspondence, legal files, contract-related files, reports, research files, retirees' chapter records, an extensive body of material documenting the schools crises of 1967-1968 and a collection of material from the files of former CSA president and CSA historian Jack Zuckerman.
Separated Materials
Photographs were separated and established as the Council of School Supervisors and Administrators Photographs (PHOTOS 265). Audio materials were separated and established as the Council of School Supervisors and Administrators Audio (OH 076).
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Ernest Logan (CSA President) on behalf of the Council of School Supervisors and Administrators, 2007; at the same time, former CSA president Jack Zuckerman donated an additional six feet of material from his personal files. The accession number associated with this collection is 2007.007.
https://www.csa-nyc.org/ and http://www.csawf.org/ were initially selected by curators and captured through the use of The California Digital Library's Web Archiving Service in 2014-2015 as part of the Labor Unions and Organizations (U.S.) Web Archive. In 2015, these websites were migrated to Archive-It. Archive-It uses web crawling technology to capture websites at a scheduled time and displays only an archived copy, from the resulting WARC file, of the website. In 2019, https://elipd.org/ was added to the web archive. The accession number associated with this website is 2020.003.
Scope and Content Note
The small portion of the collection that is arranged by subject includes images of a miscellany of various events, conventions, meetings, schools, strikes, demonstrations, rallies, picket lines and a Labor Day parade, shot between 1957 and 2000, as well as portraits of individuals, including CSA leaders such as Jack Zuckerman, Donald Singer, and Peter O'Brien. The bulk of the collection, however, consists of images published, or selected for possible publication, in the union's newspaper, CSA News, for its volumes 8 through 34 (between 1974 and 2001). These are arranged by volume number (within print and contact sheet and negative series), with little or no description of their contents. Although most of the contact sheets in the CSA News series have corresponding negatives, and the series include some prints with matching negatives, it is doubtful that these files contain all of the images published in CSA News.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
United Federation of Teachers Records. (WAG 22)
Council of School Supervisors and Administrators Photographs. (PHOTOS 265)
Arrangement
Organized into 6 series: I, Minutes II, General Files III, Jacob (Jack) Zuckerman Files IV, Council of School Supervisors and Administrators Retirees Chapter Files, 1972-2007 V, Oversize Periodicals on Decentralization and Ocean Hill-Brownsville, 1968-1969 VI, Archived Websites, April 2014-ongoing
Arranged alphabetically within each series.
Historical/Biographical Note
The Council of School Supervisors and Administrators (formerly the Council of Supervisors and Administrators) represents principals, assistant principals and other administrators at all levels within the New York City school system. Its origins are in the post-World War II years, when supervisors in various categories (including assistant superintendents, principals, assistant principals, chairmen of departments, junior principals and principals of youth and adult centers) were represented by a number of separate, and relatively powerless, associations. By the 1950s there was a growing interest in lobbying in a more unified way for improvements in pay and terms of employment. By 1960 representatives of eleven supervisors' associations were meeting together to recommend specific salary index levels for each association. As a result of their efforts the Superintendent of Schools endorsed this indexing proposal and it became state law through the Marchi Bill of 1962.
In 1961, in the course of pressing for indexing legislation, the eleven associations came together to form a Council of Supervisory Associations of the Public Schools of New York City. Under the direction of early presidents such as Benjamin Strumpf (1961-1963), Walter Degnan (1963-1965; 1968-1970), and Stuart Lucey (1965-1967) the Council began to collect dues (indexed to salary levels), hired paid staff, and pressed for the right to represent supervisors before the Superintendent and to help shape policy. The Council's first full-time Executive Director, Al Morrison, was hired in 1964. Eventually three additional associations joined the Council, which adopted the name Council of Supervisors and Administrators (CSA) in 1968.
The Board of Education recognized the Council officially and, in 1965, signed a welfare agreement that made the Council de facto welfare (benefits) agents for all supervisors.
In its early years some supervisors had agitated for a trade union form of organization (similar to the United Federation of Teachers); this proposal had failed in a narrow vote but the demand for a more militant form of representation, with dues check-off and collective bargaining, was revived in the crisis conditions that developed around the move toward system decentralization in the late 1960s. In the face of a rising tide of demands for community control and racial tensions, with flash points such as I.S. 201 in Harlem and the Ocean Hill-Brownsville District in Brooklyn, the UFT went on strike in September 1967. Soon the Association of Assistant Principals declared a work stoppage and were joined by other CSA members. A number of principals and assistant principals requested, and got, transfers, maid claims of community harassment.
The result was turmoil within CSA. On the one hand the organization rejected many of the City's decentralization plans; on the other, attempts to forge CSA affiliation with the UFT or the Teamsters met with no success. Nevertheless, in the face of opposition from some CSA members, CSA joined with the UFT to lobby in Albany against a decentralization bill. A special committee of CSA, under new president Walter Degnan, was appointed to monitor developments during the turbulent summer of 1968. In an atmosphere of continued internal dissension, agreement on seeking a contract finally emerged, and negotiations were begun. The City agreed to participate in collective bargaining and, in the fall of 1969, a contract (the first such contract for school supervisors in the country) was ratified overwhelmingly and grievance machinery was set up.
The AFL-CIO chartered the School Administrators and Supervisors Organizing Committee (spearheaded by CSA, which became SASOC, Local 1) in 1971. Renamed and re-chartered as the American Federation of School Supervisors (AFSA) in 1978, the national organization now has affiliates across the country.
In recent decades, the CSA has functioned as a fully-fledged trade-union, aggressively defending staffing, salary and benefits levels and tenure for supervisors; managing a Welfare Fund; lobbying on all legislative matters affecting public education (often in cooperation with the United Federation of Teachers and other public employee unions); providing educational and training opportunities for members; raising issues of workplace health and safety; and creating a more than 9,000-strong retirees' chapter. The union has also steadily expanded its outreach efforts, both to members and to the general public, through its bulletins and newspaper (CSA News), its web site, and its press conferences, television appearances, and radio ads.
In 2003 the CSA, along with other plaintiffs, won a notable victory in court against the Bloomberg Administration's proposal to eliminate Community School Boards. This effort, and the union's many recent initiatives to work cooperatively with community and parents' groups and to join in vigorous protests against budget cuts, marks a distinct shift in emphasis from its early struggles against rapid decentralization. In a successful organizing campaign, it has brought more than 400 directors and assistant directors of day-care centers into its ranks, and in 2005 the union negotiated a pioneering day-care contract that was overwhelmingly ratified. Also in 2005, the merger of the CSA's retirees' chapter with the Retired School Supervisors and Administrators (RSSA) created a new and effective lobbying force on issues of concern to the union.
Betty S. Ostroff, The Metamorphosis of a Professional Association into a Union. [case-study of the CSA] (Ph.D. dissertation, New York University, 1973).
Jacob (Jack) Zuckerman. Manuscript notes on CSA history; columns and other writing in CSA News, 1990s-2003; "A Brief History of CSA" https://wayback.archive-it.org/6349/20150114190146/http://www.csa-nyc.org/about-csa/history, accessed June 30, 2009.
Appraisal
Archived websites are made accessible for purposes of education and research. NYU Libraries have given attribution to rights holders when possible; however, due to the nature of archival collections, we are not always able to identify this information.
If you hold the rights to materials in our archived websites that are unattributed, please let us know so that we may maintain accurate information about these materials.
If you are a rights holder and are concerned that you have found material on this website for which you have not granted permission (or is not covered by a copyright exception under US copyright laws), you may request the removal of the material from our site by submitting a notice, with the elements described below, to the special.collections@nyu.edu.
Please include the following in your notice: Identification of the material that you believe to be infringing and information sufficient to permit us to locate the material; your contact information, such as an address, telephone number, and email address; a statement that you are the owner, or authorized to act on behalf of the owner, of an exclusive right that is allegedly infringed and that you have a good-faith belief that use of the material in the manner complained of is not authorized by the copyright owner, its agent, or the law; a statement that the information in the notification is accurate and made under penalty of perjury; and your physical or electronic signature. Upon receiving a notice that includes the details listed above, we will remove the allegedly infringing material from public view while we assess the issues identified in your notice.
Clippings files.; Administrative records.; Minutes (administrative records); New York (N.Y.).; Correspondence.; Discrimination in education |z New York (State) |z New York.; Scrapbooks.; Strikes and lockouts -- Teachers -- New York (State) -- New York.; Ocean Hill-Brownsville Demonstration School District (New York, N.Y.); Schools |x Decentralization |z New York (State) |z New York.; Web sites.; American Federation of School Administrators. Local 1, Council of Supervisors and Administrators (New York, N.Y.); Zuckerman, Jacob (Jack); Association of Assistant Principals; New York (N.Y.). Board of Education; O'Brien, Peter S.; New York City Elementary School Principals Association; American Federation of School Administrators. Local 1, Council of Supervisors and Administrators (New York, N.Y.); Logan, Ernest; Zuckerman, Jacob (Jack)
- Series I: Executive Board Minutes, 1964-2006
  Scope and Content Note
  Series I: Executive Board Minutes, 1964-2006, contains minutes and associated correspondence and documents.
  - Executive Board: Minutes, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Executive Board: Minutes, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Executive Board: Minutes, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Executive Board: Minutes, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Executive Board: Minutes, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Executive Board: Minutes, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Executive Board: Minutes, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Executive Board: Minutes, 1971-1973 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Executive Board: Minutes, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Executive Board: Minutes, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Executive Board: Minutes, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Executive Board: Minutes, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Executive Board: Minutes, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Executive Board: Minutes, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Executive Board: Minutes, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Executive Board: Minutes, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Executive Board: Minutes, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Executive Board: Minutes, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Executive Board: Minutes, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Executive Board: Minutes, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Executive Board: Minutes, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Executive Board: Minutes, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Executive Board: Minutes, 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Executive Board: Minutes, 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Executive Board: Minutes, 2000-2002 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Executive Board: Minutes, 2004-2006 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Series II: General Files, 1945-2007
  Series II: General Files, 1945-2007. This series contains files documenting activity of the union itself (including conventions, bargaining, correspondence of officers and staff, district chairmen, Hotline messages and elections), as well as topical files. Well represented are materials on the CSA's relations with the NYC Board of Education and the Chancellor's Office, with the Association of Assistant Principals, the New York City Elementary School Principals Association, and other organizations. Other files document issues of special interest to the union, for example, ethnicity and bilingual education, the role of parents, performance reviews, pertinent legislation and layoffs and excessing occasioned by the City's fiscal crisis of the 1970s. A particularly extensive and rich series of files documents the bitter disputes regarding community control of schools (especially in Ocean Hill-Brownsville) that resulted in the teachers' strike of 1968-69. The CSA took shape in response to these events, and its files and scrapbooks present a minutely detailed account of events, including clippings from the local press, United federation of teachers materials, and rare flyers and ephemera illustrating the role of supervisors and administrators in the conflict.
  - Accountability, 1971-1974 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Advisory Committee: Minutes and General, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Advisory Committee: Minutes and General, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Advisory Committee: Minutes and General, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Advisory Committee: Minutes and General, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Affirmative Action (general information and Bakke Case), 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - American Association of School Administrators, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - American Federation of School Administrators, 1976-2001 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Associate Memberships Committee, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Association of Assistant Administrative Directors, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Association of Assistant Principals (AAP), Undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Association of Assistant Principals (AAP), 1957-1961 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Association of Assistant Principals (AAP), 1962 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Association of Assistant Principals (AAP), 1963-1965 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Association of Assistant Principals (AAP), 1966 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Association of Assistant Principals (AAP), 1967 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Association of Assistant Principals (AAP), 1968 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Association of Assistant Principals (AAP), 1969 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Association of Assistant Principals (AAP), 1970 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Association of Assistant Principals (AAP), 1971 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Association of Assistant Principals (AAP), 1972 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Association of Assistant Principals (AAP), 1973 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Association of Assistant Principals (AAP), 1974 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Association of Assistant Principals (AAP), 1975 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Association of Assistant Principals (AAP), 1976 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Association of Assistant Principals (AAP), 1977 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Association of Assistant Principals (AAP), 1978 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Association of Assistant Principals (AAP), 1979 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Association of Assistant Principals (AAP), 1980 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Association of Assistant Principals (AAP), 1981 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Association of Assistant Principals (AAP), 1982 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Association of Assistant Principals (AAP), 1983 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Association of Assistant Principals (AAP), 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Association of Assistant Principals (AAP), 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Association of Assistant Principals (AAP), 1988-1990 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Association of Assistant Principals (AAP), 1992 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Association of Assistant Principals (AAP), 1993-1995 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Association of Assistant Principals (AAP), 1996 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Association of Assistant Principals (AAP), 1997-1999 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Association of Assistant Principals (AAP), 2000-2002 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Association of Assistant Principals (AAP), 2003-2005 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Association of Assistant Principals (AAP), 2006-2007 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Association of Assistant Principals (AAP): Roster of Presidents, 1968-1992 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Association of Orthodox Jewish Teachers, 1975-1977; 2002-2004 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Benefits, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Benjamin Franklin High School: Acting Principal Dispute, 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Bicentennial Committee, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Bilingual Bicultural Education, 1967-1974 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Bilingual Committee, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Black trade Unionists Committee Convention, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Board of Education: History and Statistical Overview of Public Education in New York City, 1898-1998 (report) (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Board of Education: Community School Board Personnel Letters, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Board of Education: Hearing on Emergency School Assistance, 1973; 1975 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Board of Education Meetings, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Board of Education Meetings, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Board of Education Meetings, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Board of Education Meetings, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Board of Education Meetings, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Board of Education Meetings, 1975-1977 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Board of Education: Method of Selection/Structure, 1971-1975 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Board of Education: Personnel Regulations, 1969-1971 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Board of Examiners, 1970-1974; 1982 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Board of Examiners: Amendments to Bylaws, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Budget Issues, 1968-1975 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Budget Issues, 1987-1988 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Budget Crisis and Layoffs, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Calendar of Professional Activities, 1975-1976 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Calendar of Regular CSA Meetings, 1973-1974 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Chairmen's Workshop Weekend, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Chairpersons, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Chance, Boston M. et al. v. Board of Examiners (U.S. District Court) (I), 1970-1973 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Chance, Boston M. et al. v. Board of Examiners (U.S. District Court) (II), 1970-1973 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Chance, Boston M. et al. v. Board of Examiners (U.S. District Court) (III), 1970-1973 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Chance, Boston M. et al. v. Board of Examiners (U.S. District Court) (IV), 1974-1975 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Chance, Boston M. et al. v. Board of Examiners (Background), 1969-1970 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Chance, Boston M. et al. v. Board of Examiners (Background), 1971-1976 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Chance, Boston M. et al. v. Board of Examiners (Clippings), 1970-1974 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Chance, Boston M. et al. v. Board of Examiners: Tyler Decision, 1974-1975 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Chancellor: Calendar and Clippings, 1969-1971 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Chancellor's Consultation Meeting, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Chancellor's Meetings: Agenda and Minutes, 1968-1969 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Chancellor's Meetings: Agenda and Minutes, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Chancellor's Meetings: Agenda and Minutes, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Chancellor's Meetings: Agenda and Minutes, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Chancellor's Meetings: Agenda and Minutes, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Chancellor's Meetings: Agenda and Minutes, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Chancellor's Meetings: Agenda and Minutes, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Chancellor's Meetings: Agenda and Minutes, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Chancellor's Meetings: Agenda and Minutes, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Chancellor's Meetings: Agenda and Minutes, 1980-1981 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Chancellor's Meetings: Agenda and Minutes, 1982-1983 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Chancellor's Meetings: Agenda and Minutes, 1984-1985 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Chancellor's Meetings: Agenda and Minutes, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Chancellor's Meetings: Agenda and Minutes, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Chancellor's Meetings: Agenda and Minutes, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Chancellor's Meetings: Agenda and Minutes, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Chancellor's Meetings: Agenda and Minutes, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Child Abuse Prevention, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Church-State: School Prayer (Clippings), 1950; 1962-1963 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Community Relations Workshops, 1961-1975 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Competency Based Teachers Education (Performance Based Teachers' Education), 1971-1977 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Certificates of Competency, 1976-1978 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Comprehensive School Improvement Plan, 1985-1986 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Commission on Minimum Standards, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Conference: Educational Leadership, 1984-1989 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Conference: Educational Leadership, 1990-1995 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Conference: Educational Leadership, 1996-1999 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Conference: Educational Leadership, 2000-2006 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Conference: New York State Public Employee Conference, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Conference: UFT/CSA Joint Weekend, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Conference: UFT/CSA Mini- Weekend, 1973; 1975 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Constitution and Bylaws, 1969-2004 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Constitution Subcommittee, 1966-1975 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Contract Demands, 1975-1977 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Contract/Agreement, 1969-1972 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Contract/Agreement, 1972-1975 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Contract: Bargaining Files, 1973-1977 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Contract: Bargaining Files, 1978-1980 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Contract: Memorandum, 1998-1999 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Convention, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Convention, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 16)